Guide to the Joseph Riggs Collection relating to Kaspar Monahan, 1927-1988 CTC.1994.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Joseph Riggs Collection relating to Kaspar Monahan
1927-1988
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Riggs, Joseph H.
CTC.1994.01
8 Linear Feet (21 boxes)
Dr. Joseph Riggs, a Professor Emeritus of communications at Slippery Rock University, began collecting materials relating to the career of Kaspar 'Kap' Monahan in the 1970's. Kaspar Monahan was a reporter who served as drama editor for the Pittsburgh Press from 1932 to 1968. He conducted oral history interviews with Monahan and retrieved copies of Monahan's articles. The collection includes the tapes and transcripts from the interviews, columns written by Monahan for multiple newspapers from 1927 to 1968, and materials documenting Riggs's collection efforts.
Biography
Dr. Joseph Riggs, a Professor Emeritus of communications at Slippery Rock University, began collecting and microfilming the columns of his close friend Kaspar Monahan in the 1970's in order to preserve "a treasure trove" of film, theatre, and entertainment history. He worked systematically to retrieve and microfilm all of Monahan's writings from 1927 to 1968. He and several others conducted interviews with Monahan, which were then transcribed and compiled into a comprehensive oral history. Riggs organized an exhibit of these materials at Slippery Rock's Bailey Library in April 1983 and then had them displayed in Monahan's hometown of Salida, Colorado, the following year. He also began, but did not complete, an indexing project designed to facilitate searching of the collection.
Kaspar 'Kap' Monahan was born in Louisville, Kentucky, in 1894. His family later moved to Salida, Colorado, where he began his career writing and drawing cartoons for the high school newspaper. Monahan worked for the railroad and local theaters before a local businessman sent him to the University of Colorado to study journalism in 1922. During his time there, he wrote for the Dodo and the Silver and Gold; after graduation he worked as a reporter and drama critic for the Pueblo Chieftain, the Associated Press, the Denver Express, the Denver World, the Rocky Mountain News, and the Denver Post. He became drama editor for the Pittsburgh Press in 1932. During his tenure, Monahan became a nationally known figure through his reviews of theater productions and films, writings about the entertainment industry in general, and interviews with performers, writers, and producers including Clark Gable, Mae West, and Cecil B. DeMille. He retired from the Press in 1968 but continued to write articles until his death in 1980 at age 86.
Scope and Content Notes
The collection contains copies of over 10,000 columns written by Monahan for the Rocky Mountain News, Denver Post, and Pittsburgh Press between 1929 and 1968. Columns that appeared in the Pittsburgh Press between March 1954 and January 1968 are also available on microfiche. The Riggs Materials include correspondence, press releases, and notes pertaining to Dr. Riggs' efforts to collect the columns, index them, and make them publicly available. The Oral History series includes audio reels and cassette tapes of the interviews, individual transcripts, and a manuscript compiling the various interviews into one narrative.
Arrangement
Series I. Columns, 1927-1968
Series II. Riggs Materials, 1968, 1980-1988
Series III. Oral History, 1974-1977, 1980
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dr. Joseph H. Riggs in 1994.
Existence and Location of Copies
Columns that appeared in the Pittsburgh Press from March 1954 to January 1968 are also available both on paper and on microfiche.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
While the majority of the material are papers, the collection also includes 12 audio tapes, 12 cassette tapes, and a box of microfiche. The audio reels are not available for use, but the cassette tapes can be used at Stark Media Services and the microfiche at the Microforms Room in Hillman Library.
Custodial History
The materials were originally collected by Dr. Riggs and stored at Slippery Rock State College (now Slippery Rock University of Pennsylvania), Slippery Rock, Pennsylvania.
Separated Material
The monograph, 100 Years in the Heart of the Rockies, by Cynthia J. Pasquale has been cataloged separately and is located in the Special Collections general book collection.
Previous Citation
Joseph Riggs Collection relating to Kaspar Monahan, 1927-1988, CTC.1994.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Joseph Riggs Collection relating to Kaspar Monahan, 1927-1988, CTC.37, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Theater; Theater critics; Newspaper employees; Theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Reviews; Performing arts -- Reviews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Actors -- Interviews -- United States; Rocky Mountain News (Denver, Colo.: 1937); Actresses -- Interviews -- United States; Theater -- Colorado -- Denver -- Reviews; Motion pictures -- Reviews -- United States; Dramatic criticism -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Dramatic criticism -- Colorado -- Denver; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Denver (Colo.); Microfiche; Audiotapes; Audiocassettes; Monahan, Kaspar; Riggs, Joseph H.; Slippery Rock State College
- Columns, 1927-1968; I.
  Scope and Contents note
  Monahan wrote over 10,000 columns for the Rocky Mountain News (spanning January 1927 to August 1931), the Denver Post (October 1931 to February 1932), and the Pittsburgh Press (June 1932 to July 1968). These newspaper articles are arranged chronologically. Each folder contains two months of columns. Columns that appeared in the Pittsburgh Press between March 1954 and January 1968 are also available on microfiche.
  - Columns, January 1927-December 1930 (Box 1, Folder 01-14)
  - Columns, January 1931-October 1933 (Box 2, Folder 01-15)
  - Columns, November 1933-December 1935 (Box 3, Folder 01-13)
  - Columns, January 1936-June 1938 (Box 4, Folder 01-15)
  - Columns, July 1938-June 1940 (Box 5, Folder 01-12)
  - Columns, July 1940-June 1942 (Box 6, Folder 01-12)
  - Columns, July 1942-December 1944 (Box 7, Folder 01-15)
  - Columns, January 1945-June 1947 (Box 8, Folder 01-15)
  - Columns, July 1947-June 1949 (Box 9, Folder 01-12)
  - Columns, July 1949-December 1951 (Box 10, Folder 01-15)
  - Columns, January 1952-June 1954 (Box 11, Folder 01-15)
  - Columns, July 1954-December 1956 (Box 12, Folder 01-15)
  - Columns, March 1957-June 1959 (Box 13, Folder 01-14)
  - Columns, July 1959-December 1961 (Box 14, Folder 01-15)
  - Columns, January 1962-June 1964 (Box 15, Folder 01-15)
  - Columns, July 1964-December 1966 (Box 16, Folder 01-15)
  - Columns, January 1967-July 1968 (Box 17, Folder 01-10)
  - Columns on microfiche, March 1954-January 1968 (Box 18)
- Riggs Materials, 1968, 1980-1988; II.
  The majority of this series relates to Dr. Riggs' efforts to collect Monahan's columns and make them available at Slippery Rock University. The materials include press releases, project notes, and publicity fliers as well as correspondence between Riggs and the Monahan family.
  - Press releases about the Monahan Collection, 1980-1986 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Indexing project notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Microfilming project notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Slippery Rock University Monahan exhibit planning materials, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Slippery Rock University Monahan exhibit guide/program, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Slippery Rock University Kaspar Monahan Lecture publicity, 1982-1985 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Articles about Kaspar Monahan, 1965 and 1988 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence from Monahan to Riggs (including his last column, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence from Monahan Family to Riggs, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified photograph (possibly of Kaspar Monahan), undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified press photographs (possibly from Hadrian VII), undated (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous materials, undated (Box 19, Folder 12)
- Oral History, 1974-1977, 1980; III.
  This series contains the audio tapes, cassettes, and transcripts generated by a series of oral history interviews conducted by Riggs and three of his colleagues. All of the media contain conversations with Monahan except for one reel, in which Riggs interviews Carl Apone, another writer for the Pittsburgh Press, for his reflections on Monahan. There is also a comprehensive oral history narrative comprised of snippets from the individual interviews. The media are identified by the name of the interviewer(s) and the date, if any, provided on the cases. The audio tapes are not available for use, but the cassette tapes can be used at Stark Media Services in Hillman Library.
  - Typed transcript of interview with Orley Holtan, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Handwritten transcript of interview with Orley Holtan, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Typed transcript of interview with Mary Garfield, February 17, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Typed transcript of interview with Mary Garfield, February 26, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Photocopy of handwritten transcript of interview with Mary Garfield, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Handwritten transcript of interview with Mary Garfield, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Handwritten transcript of interview with Ed Walsh, 1977 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Typed transcripts of interviews with Joe Riggs, undated (Box 20, Folder 08-09)
  - Compiled oral history narrative, undated (Box 20, Folder 10-11)
  - Orley Holtan, January 29,1975 (Box 21, Cassette 1-2)
  - Orley Holtan, January 30,1975 (Box 21, Cassette 3)
  - Mary Garfield, February 17, 1976 (Box 21, Cassette 4-5)
  - Mary Garfield, February 24, 1976 (Box 21, Cassette 6)
  - Mary Garfield, February 26, 1976 (Box 21, Cassette 7-8)
  - Unidentified, April 1, 1976 (Box 21, Cassette 9)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 21, Cassette 10-12)
  - Unidentified, June 24, 1974 (Box 21, Tape 1)
  - Orley Holtan and Joe Riggs, June 27, 1974 (Box 21, Tape 2)
  - Unidentified, July 3, 1974 (Box 21, Tape 3)
  - Orley Holtan, January 29, 1975 (Box 21, Tape 04-05)
  - Mary Garfield, February 17, 1976 (Box 21, Tape 6)
  - Mary Garfield, February 26, 1976 (Box 21, Tape 7)
  - Mary Garfield, April 1, 1976 (Box 21, Tape 8)
  - Ed Walsh, May 12, 1977 (Box 21, Tape 09-11)
  - Carl Apone on Monahan, interviewed by Joe Riggs, November 10, 1980 (Box 21, Tape 12)